<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Account of the great defeat that Major General Kirk gave the Irish forces near Charlemont under the command of the Lord Strabane and Colonel Gordon O-Neal likewise the transactions of the late King James in Ireland since the arrival of His Grace the Duke de Schomberg.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 3 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25249</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A296A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28925</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10776304</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10776304</idno>
            <idno type="VID">45838</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25249)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45838)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1413:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Account of the great defeat that Major General Kirk gave the Irish forces near Charlemont under the command of the Lord Strabane and Colonel Gordon O-Neal likewise the transactions of the late King James in Ireland since the arrival of His Grace the Duke de Schomberg.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>l broadside.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J.C.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ireland --  History --  1660-1688.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History, Military --  1603-1714.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:45838:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 1 -->
            <head>An Account of the Great DEFEAT THAT <hi>Major General Kirk</hi> Gave the Iriſh Forces near CHARLEMONT, Under the Command of the Lord <hi>Strabane,</hi> and Colonel <hi>Gordon-O-Neal.</hi> Likewiſe the Tranſactions of the <hi>Late King Iames in Ireland,</hi> Since the Arrival Of His Grace the Duke <hi>de SCHOMBERG.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>YEſterday Sixty Sail arrived here from <hi>Carrickfergus,</hi> confirming the Account I gave you in my laſt, of the Surrender of that Place, after a Siege of Eight Days, during which time were heav'd into it a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Bombs. Seven Men of War Batter'd it for the ſpace of a whole Night, ſo that it is now little elſe ſave a Heap of Ruines.</p>
            <p>The Earl of <hi>Antrim</hi> being Governor thereof, Duke <hi>Schombergh</hi> Compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented him and his Lady with his own Horſes, and a conſiderable Convoy, to ſecure them from the Rabble. The firſt Bomb that fell into the Town having a long Fuze, did not Fire ſuddenly, but Fizzing a little, a dozen igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant <hi>Iriſh</hi> of that Gariſon came about it, and at their Coſt experienc't its Fatal Influence.</p>
            <p>Major General <hi>Kirk</hi> with his Forces, and thoſe from <hi>Enniskellen,</hi> upon their March towards <hi>Charlemont,</hi> we are told, were Attack'd by 800 Horſe under the Lord <hi>Strabane,</hi> and a Body of 1200 Foot under Colonel <hi>Gordon-O-Neal,</hi> and Colonel <hi>Maxwel.</hi> The Fight was obſtinate and bloody for ſome time, but, at length, the Lord <hi>Strabane,</hi> with 30 leading Officers being kill'd, the <hi>Iriſh</hi> betook themſelves to Flight, leaving above 300 dead on the place, and on our ſide 70.</p>
            <p>The Gariſon of <hi>Charlemont,</hi> upon the News of our Succeſs, drew out their proviſions and Artillery, with the choiceſt of their Baggage; and 'tis thought they'll deſert, and blow up the Caſtle.</p>
            <p>We are informed by credible Perſons from <hi>Dublin,</hi> that King <hi>James</hi>'s Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers deſert daily, and that a Captain and Lieutenant were ſhot upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count. The late King has left <hi>Dublin</hi> very diſconſolate, and carried with him the Batchelors of the Mint. 'Tis ſaid he is gone for <hi>Athlone,</hi> intending to wait there the Succeſs of his Army. He has fortified that Gariſon, and ſent 300 Load of Ammunition thither, having given Orders to the Lords <hi>Golmoy</hi> and <hi>Dungan</hi> to break down the Bridge of the <hi>Newry,</hi> and guard that Paſs with a conſiderable Body of Horſe and Foot. Some of the Lords of the <hi>Pale</hi> have ſent to treat with Duke <hi>Schombergh,</hi> in order to accept of his Conditions of Indempnity.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="license">
            <p>Licens'd</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Sept. 5. 1689.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>J. C.</hi> near <hi>Fleet-Bridge,</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
